Guide to the Theodore Carswell Hume Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Theodore Carswell Hume Papers
1929-1969
RG 116
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(7 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and tributes document the life and work of this prominent Congregational clergyman. Theodore Carswell Hume (1904-1943) was a Congregational minister in Chicago and California. He died in Europe while serving as emissary of the American churches under the auspices of the American Church Committee on Relief and Reconstruction and the World Council of Churches.
Hume, Theodore Carswell, 1904-1943
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. T. C. Hume and Mrs. Charlotte Freeman.
Biographical / Historical
1904 Born in India; childhood spent in China. His father, Edward H. Hume was a medical doctor in China and later president of Yale-in-China.
1918-1921 Attended the Hill School
1925 B.A., Yale
1925-1926 French government scholarship at the University of Paris
1926-1927 Rhodes Scholarship: New College, Oxford, England
1928 Began formal theological education at Mansfield College, Oxford
1930 B.D., Union Theological Seminary, New York
1930 Ordained as Congregational minister
1931 Minister: Summerdale Congregational Church, Chicago
1932-1939 Minister: New England Church, Chicago Chairman of the World Friendship Commission of the Chicago Church Federation and president of the Chicago Peace Council
1937 Secretary of the subcommittee on the Church and the War at the Oxford World Church Conference.
1940-1943 Served parish in Claremont, CA; he was married with five children. Vice President of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
1943 Sep Went to Europe as emissary of the American churches, under the auspices of the American Church Committee on Relief and Reconstruction and the World Council of Churches.
1943 Oct Died when Swedish neutral plane carrying him from London to Stockholm was shot down.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Collected Material
Dating from 1929 to 1969, the material includes correspondence, writings, printed material, and memorabilia of Theodore Carswell Hume. There are two chronologically arranged sequences for each series, because the material was donated to the library at separate times. The writings of Series II form the largest portion of the collection. Included under the broad category of "writings" are sermons, addresses, prayers, service outlines, notes, papers, and memoranda. Hume was clearly a rising star in the ecumenical scene and his death was a blow for many; this sense of loss is reflected in the many tributes to Hume that form part of this collection.
The papers of Hume's parents, Edward H. and Lotta C. Hume, are located at Sterling Memorial Library.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and Notes
III. Collected Material
World War, 1939-1945 -- Religious aspects; Clergy; Hume, Theodore Carswell, 1904-1943; World Council of Churches
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Original sequence
    - Correspondence of TCH, 1931-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence following death of TCH, 1943-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Addendum
    - Correspondence of TCH, 1934-1943 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Re. TCH mission as representative of American churches in Europe for the WCC, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence following death of TCH; incl. to from Edward H. Hume, Robert L. Calhoun, 1943-1951 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Re. proposed posthumous publication of TCH writings, 1943-1955 (Box 7, Folder 49)
- Writings and Notes, Series II
  - Original sequence
    - Writings and notes, 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3-13)
    - Writings and notes, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
    - Incl. notebook of sermons and prayers compiled for possible publication. (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
    - Card file, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Addendum
    - Writings and notes, 1929-1940 Mar (Box 4, Folder 26-34)
    - Writings and notes, 1940 Apr-1942 May (Box 5, Folder 36-40)
    - Writings and notes, 1942 Jun-1943, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 41-45)
- Collected Material, Series III
  - Original sequence
    - Printed material, 1937-1943 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Memorabilia, 1943-1948, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    - Photographic portrait of Theodore Carswell Hume (Box OV-d4)
  - Addendum
    - Re. New England Church, Chicago, 1935-1939 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Re. Claremont Congregational Church, Claremont, CA, 1939-1944 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Poems, prayers, quotations, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Biographical documentation, 1942-1944 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Writings by others, 1939-1952 (Box 7, Folder 54)